Guide to the Philip C. Landers Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Philip C. Landers Papers
1913-1972
RG 191
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, collected materials, and biographical material document the life and work of Philip C. Landers. Landers and his wife, Ethna, both pursued careers in Christian education. Landers was a founder of the "University of Life" movement in Minnesota. He later worked for the International Council of Religious Education in Chicago, which merged into the National Council of Churches, based in New York. He coordinated the nationwide introduction and interpretation of the new Revised Standard Version of the Bible in the early 1950s.
Landers, Philip C.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Laurence G. Landers, 1995.
Biographical / Historical
1897 January28 Philip Corliss Landers born in Middletown, MA, second son of the Reverend and Mrs. Warren Prince Landers
1915-1918 Following graduation from high school in Brockton, MA worked for shoe company and for Massachusetts Total Abstinence Society
1918-1919 Served in U.S. Army
1919-1922 Worked for Prudential Life Insurance Company in Brockton
1922-1927 Attended Boston University School of Religious Education for undergraduate and graduate degrees; served as Director of Religious Education in area church
1927 Married Ethna V. Jones, who also graduated from the Boston University School of Religious Education and remained active as a Director of Christian Education in various churches throughout her husband's career.
1927-1930 Served as Director of Christian Education at Trinity Methodist Church in Springfield, MA
1930-1936 On staff of Hennepin Avenue Methodist Church, Minneapolis, MN. Began the University of Life program.
1936-1941 PCL began work for Minnesota Council of Religious Education (later Council of Churches). Set up interdenominational Leadership Training Schools across the state and interdenominational Universities of Life. Started the Faribault Summer School of Christian Education.
1941-1950 Director of The Laymen's Crusade for Christian Education and Director of Public Relations for the International Council of Religious Education in Chicago. Became Associate General Secretary in 1946.
1950-1962 ICRE merged with seven other national interdenominational organizations to form the National Council of Churches in 1950. PCL one of three Administrative Secretaries of the NCC, based at Interchurch Center in New York, overseeing Treasury Office, Publications Office, Personnel Office, Business Office, and Fund Raising.
1952 Received honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters from Hamline University, St. Paul, MN
1952 Coordinated the nationwide introduction of the new Revised Standard Version of the Bible
1962 Retired to Minnesota, with winter home in Brownsville,TX; provided volunteer service to Walker Community Church and Union Congregational Church in Hackensack, MN.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains valuable documentation of the life and work of a layperson who worked for state and national interdenominational organizations and was instrumental in establishing the University of Life religious education program. The documentation in this collection related to the Revised Standard Version of the Bible complements the archives of the Standard Bible Committee found in Yale Divinity School Library Record Group No. 70.
Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to and from Philip C. Landers during the course of his career. Series II and III relate to programs that were central to Landers' work - the University of Life and the introduction of the Revised Standard Version of the Bible. Series IV contains printed material related to various organizations with which Landers was involved. Series V contains detailed biographical information about Landers and his family.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Related to University of Life
III. Related to Revised Standard Version of the Bible
IV. Collected Material
V. Biographical Information
Bible -- Versions; Christian education; Educators; Landers, Philip C.; International Council of Religious Education
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Of PCL
    - Correspondence alphabetized by sender/recipient: C - S (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Other correspondence
    - Related to National Council of Churches of Christ, 1962 Feb (Box 1, Folder 2)
- University of Life, Series II
  - Beginnings - Hennepin Ave Methodist Church, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochures from other Churches' schools (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles re University of Life (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Re. Revised Standard Version of Bible, Series III
  - Proposal for a Bible week honoring RSVB, 1948 Mar (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Bible goes to Press, 1952 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - RSVB observances, 1952 Sep 28-Oct 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interpretation.and promotion of RSVB, 1945-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report of Committee on Use and Understanding of the Bible, 1955 Feb (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Program Guide on Use and Understanding of Bible, 1958 Nov (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes of Committee on Use and Understanding, 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Collected Material, Series IV
  - The Interchurch Center, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The International Council of Religious Education (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Book: re. First Parish Congregational Church, Brockton, MA, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book: Pastor's Worship Aids, 1913-39 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Books: Pastor's Worship Aids (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Book: Adventure in Jade by James Kraft; other articles by Kraft, 1947,1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Misc. items (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Biographical Information, Series V
  - Personal Life History (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hamline University Honorary Degree, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Certificate and Acknowledgements (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Newsclippings, press releases (Box 3, Folder 24)